hi there Simon here thank you for
joining me today and I'm sure that when
you create a graph you have a pretty
thorough understanding of what the key
messages will be however unless specific
steps are taken to show these to your
audience it can leave these crucial
insights uncovered let's take a look at
an example this data is from a company
that's looking to track its overall
complaint volumes over time each line
represents a year from 2022 to partway
through
2024 and to provide the audience with as
much detail as possible a data table has
been added providing the granular
numbers behind the lines in the chart
this is a fairly common approach but
with this amount of information and in
this style there is a risk that our
audience isn't going to be able to
recover those vital insights indeed as I
look at this graph I'm left wondering
what is it that the original Creator was
looking to share when I initially create
a graph I will typically spend a few
moments writing a sentence or to
conveying the key takeaways that I can
retrieve from it identifying these can
help me understand how I might draw my
audience's attention to them when I
present the information and now you've
had a moment or two with this graph I'm
curious what interesting insights have
you managed to identify now of course
you might have some different takeaways
to me and that's absolutely fine but
I've highlighted the following three
first of all we have this high point of
complaints in April 2022 of 430
then we see a decreasing Trend
throughout 2022 into 2023 and the
beginning of
2024 reducing to a record low of 118 in
January
2024 but then we see from the beginning
of 2024 January onwards the complaint
levels are beginning to rise now I have
these outlined I can begin to refine my
visual with the intention of ensuring
that these insights are clearly visible
to begin with I'm going to remove the
data table whilst having precise numbers
available can be useful in some
situations I think in this case it
distracts from the main purpose of our
graph which is to see the trends of the
data I'm going to take the opportunity
now to clean up the general formatting
of my visual this comprises a number of
simple yet important formatting steps
first of all I'm going to remove the
chart border and grid lines going to
clean up my horizontal and vertical axes
before rewriting and aligning the chart
title instead of using a legend I'm
going to take the opportunity to
directly label the lines and finally
format the lines by making them a little
bit thicker and removing the color now I
have a blank canvas to bring my
takeaways to life reflecting on my first
Insight the highest level of complaints
there in April I can choose to highlight
this with a combination of techniques
I'll update the title make the line
darker and add an annotation reading the
title now I have a clear understanding
of what I'm looking for and conf find
that information easily in the view now
this is a good start but I feel we can
improve the visual further by adjusting
its layout currently we have each year
plotted separately so it's a little bit
difficult to assess the longer term
Trend changing the horizontal axis to a
consistent timeline with just one line
will allow me to bring my other
takeaways to life with this view it's
far easier to see that downward trend of
complaints that began in April 201 22
and continued all the way through to
January 2024 my second takeaway once
again I can bring this to life using
similar focusing techniques as before
note I've used blue here which conveys a
slightly more friendly more optimistic
tone than the sterile black from the
previous example more appropriate for
the good news that's being shared with
this
takeaway now if you're curious on how
some of these changes have been made I
recommend checking out our on demand
video course over 75 minutes delving
into real world strategies and
techniques to enhancing your PowerPoint
presentations I'll put a link in the
description but if you use code YouTube
10 you'll receive 10% off that sign up
price all right let's tackle our third
takeaway now despite the good news we
should be wary that this most recent
data does show an increase in the number
of complaints it could well be of course
this is a shortterm anomaly but it's
certainly worth highlighting and
suggesting investigation occurs to
better understand the increase I'm going
to use a different color here Orange
it's a more attention grabbing Hue than
the blue I used
previously we've managed to make changes
to our visuals to incorporate each of
those main takeaways but what if we want
to combine all of those insights into
one well depending on how you
communicate this information there are a
couple of different approaches you can
take first of you're presenting live you
can articulate each of these key
takeaways with the use of Animation
giving you an opportunity to talk
through additional background context
and giving your audience a chance to
understand one aspect of the visual
before moving on to the next or if this
information needs to be conveyed using a
static one-page overview we can use a
complementary color set one with a high
degree of contrast which allows both
sides of the story to be presented at
the same time and as we ar presenting
this information live we can include
some of the aspects that we might have
said verbally by way of annotations and
additional contexts and of course
including our final recommended action
we started with a visual that had a lot
of information but didn't really convey
anything meaningful but by taking a step
back and thinking about those important
observations we've been able to adapt
our graph bringing each of those
insights to life in a clear way for our
audience for more examples of visual
Transformations do check out our
makeovers playlist and until next time
thank you very much for watching and
have a great great day